<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>realexapp</title><description>realexapp</description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/blog</link><item><title>RERA timeline: Chronology of events leading to regulation of realty sector</title><description><![CDATA[The long-pending real estate regulatory Act (RERA) has finally become a law from May 1, 2017, bringing in the much-needed transparency and setting accountability in the unorganised real estate sector. Developers will now have to get all their ongoing and new projects registered with regulatory authorities. Real estate agents also have three months to register themselves. From keeping 70% of a project's funds in a separate bank account to penal provisions for developers, agents and home buyers,<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_d53a7074d3a240ba8cbc06d728e5a82d%7Emv2.jpg/v1/fill/w_626%2Ch_271/577c7f_d53a7074d3a240ba8cbc06d728e5a82d%7Emv2.jpg"/>]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2018/01/31/RERA-timeline-Chronology-of-events-leading-to-regulation-of-realty-sector</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2018/01/31/RERA-timeline-Chronology-of-events-leading-to-regulation-of-realty-sector</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 11:06:11 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_d53a7074d3a240ba8cbc06d728e5a82d~mv2.jpg"/><div>The long-pending real estate regulatory Act (RERA) has finally become a law from May 1, 2017, bringing in the much-needed transparency and setting accountability in the unorganised real estate sector. Developers will now have to get all their ongoing and new projects registered with regulatory authorities. Real estate agents also have three months to register themselves. From keeping 70% of a project's funds in a separate bank account to penal provisions for developers, agents and home buyers, RERA looks to cover all the bases to clean the real estate sector.  Here's the chronology of events leading to regulation of real estate sector including both residential and commercial segments from May 1, 2017:</div><div>May 2008: Ministry of HUPA (Ministry of Housing and Urban Poverty Alleviation) prepares a concept paper on regulation of real estate sector and a model law for legislation by States/Union Territories.</div><div>2011: Conference of Ministers of Housing in 2011 suggests a central law for the regulation of real estate sector.</div><div>July 2011: Ministry of Law and Justice suggests central legislation for regulation</div><div>June 2013: Union Cabinet approves Real Estate Bill, 2013.</div><div>August 2013: Real Estate Bill introduced in Rajya Sabha and referred to Standing Committee.</div><div>February 2014: Report of Standing Committee laid on the Tables of both Houses of Parliament.</div><div>February 2014: Attorney General upholds validity of central law for regulation of the Real Estate sector.</div><div>April 2015: Union Cabinet approves official amendments based on recommendations of Standing Committee.</div><div>May 2015: Matter referred to the Select Committee of Rajya Sabha.</div><div>July, 2015: Report of Select Committee tabled in Rajya Sabha</div><div>December 2015: Real Estate Bill, 2015 incorporating several modifications based on Select Committee report and stakeholder consultations approved by the Union Cabinet.</div><div>March 10, 2016: Rajya Sabha passes The Real Estate (Regulation &amp; Development) Bill, 2016.</div><div>March 15, 2016: Lok Sabha passes the Bill as passed by Rajya Sabha.</div><div>March 25, 2016: President gives assent to the Bill.</div><div>April 26, 2016: 59 Sections of the Act notified, making them effective from May 1, 2016, enabling preparation of Real Estate Rules, setting up of Regulatory Authorities and other infrastructure.</div><div>April 19, 2017: Remaining 32 Sections of the Act notified making them effective from May 1st this year requiring registration of projects within three months from tomorrow.</div><div>May 1, 2017: The Real Estate (Regulation and Development) Act or RERA comes into force, bringing in the new era begins for the development of real estate sector in an atmosphere of investor confidence.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Analyzing Real Estate Technology Market</title><description><![CDATA[After the industrial revolution, countries were motivated to build large number of buildings to house the migrating resident, evolving industries and offices. Also in the race to dominate and hold position as global leadership, many cities were tasked to design large residential townships in outskirts and a central downtown, which personified the foothold they had in the economic growth. This led to building of huge infrastructure in residential, industrial and office space. Many cities built<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_7453823048734c1781793802d085de4d%7Emv2.jpg"/>]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2017/06/29/Analyzing-Real-Estate-Technology-Market</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2017/06/29/Analyzing-Real-Estate-Technology-Market</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_7453823048734c1781793802d085de4d~mv2.jpg"/><div> After the industrial revolution, countries were motivated to build large number of buildings to house the migrating resident, evolving industries and offices. Also in the race to dominate and hold position as global leadership, many cities were tasked to design large residential townships in outskirts and a central downtown, which personified the foothold they had in the economic growth. This led to building of huge infrastructure in residential, industrial and office space. Many cities built downtowns with imposing Skyscrapers from 60-100 floors and accommodating several 1000s offices within a single building. Many large corporations built or leased out entire such buildings and used them to showcase their brand image. Such magnanimous infrastructural to build cities developments have led to the emergence and evolution of computerized automation in building management for residential, commercial and industrial space.</div><div>Many technology solutions have emerged over time in this space. The following analyzes the technology market and trends.</div><div>Industry and Value Chain</div><div>The Real Estate industry users can be broadly classified in to the following industry value chain:</div><div><div>Residential - Single-family &amp; Multifamily residential, Apartments, Row-houses, Villas</div><div>Commercial – Offices, Education-schools-universities, Hospitals-healthcare</div><div>Retail - Malls, Shopping centres, Entertainment plazas, Movie theatres</div><div>Hospitality – Hotels, Leisure-style resorts, Hospitality properties</div><div>Industrial – Manufacturing &amp; production, Warehouses, Distribution, Logistics properties</div><div>Alternative Real Estate – Student housing, Storage houses, Premium retail (automobiles)</div><div>Communities, Building Owners Association Management – Residential &amp; Commercial</div></div><div>Real Estate Market Place</div><div>The properties business has a tertiary market place for property sales, leasing and consulting that includes:</div><div><div>Property Sales and Lease Brokerages: These are brokerages involved in providing services for leasing, selling, buying, home improvement and property management. In matured markets is dominated by agencies like Re/Max, RoyalLePage, Century21 etc.</div><div>Property Management and Consulting: These commercial agencies such as Colliers, Jones Lang La Salle (JLL), Cushman &amp; Wakefield, Knight &amp; Frank, CBRE whose primary focus is for large scale leasing, property and facility management, capital markets investment, project and development services, consulting and research to help real estate community</div><div>Shared Office Space: Companies like Regus, ServCorp, Signature, Kora that provide a network of offices for home based business to multi-national corporations. They take the entire or a majority of the building on lease-hold bases and sub-let it on fractional lease bases for office and commercial use</div><div>REITs – Real Estate Investment Trusts (pronounced as “REETZ”): These are organizations that build, manage and operate buildings for cash flow such as Brookfield REIT, Rio-Tinto REIT, Emirates REIT</div></div><div>Real Estate Software Market</div><div>With the introduction of IBM-client server computing and software programming, several niche real estate software solutions found their way between 1980’s – 2000. Further post 2000 dot.com evolution led to emergence of portal based solutions for cloud computing and transaction processing. Further with the launch of smart phone devices in 2007 and emergence of mobile-device (phone, tablet) computing, many vendors envisaged on moving simple-medium complexity transactions using a mobile interface. Most of these cater to the requirements in bits-and-pieces.</div><div>These can be broadly grouped into strategic categories:</div><div>1. Client-Server implementation</div><div>2. SaaS (Software-as-a-Service) OR Subscription</div><div>3. Mobile-Web Solutions</div><div>The industry software solutions evolved in a fragmented fashion and can further be classified as under following depending upon their features and nature of application:</div><div><div>ERP (Enterprise Resource Planning) &amp; Accounting Software: Like any other business organization, most property business required to maintain their day-to-day books of accounts and record transactions. It also assists with preparing year-end financial statements. However as a process most of this is done after-the-fact once the vendor generates the invoice or the sales team closes sales deal. It does not or very sparsely allows direct interaction with the end-user and consumer.</div><div>CRM (Customer Relationship Management): The introduction of cloud based computing that allowed user to login to online portal and complete a transaction took its space in the real estate industry as well. One of the most adopted solutions on this platform is CRM solution. These are solutions that allow users to maintain enquiry-to-order process and customer profiles through their web based portal solutions. A plethora had these had been designed during the Dot.com boom and very quickly died away in the bust. The survivors have struggled to maintain profitability within the ecosystem and have led to decline in further development.</div><div>Property Management: These are solutions that actually allow user to track sales, generate contracts, assign units to owner’s profiles, track services, manage vendors and inventory and maintain transaction records. Most of these solutions were built in the late 1990s to early 2000 when the technology was still monolithic with client-server architecture that requires heavy capital spend on technology infrastructure. This would include long lead times for procurement of hardware such as servers, racks, network switches, connection panels. Additional cost and time for installation. Further implementation costs and time from 6 months to 2 years to configure the system to be used a per the company’s requirement. Most of these systems were built for desk users and do not enable mobile computing.</div><div>Facility Management: The real estate facility management solutions are designed to manage space and assignment of facilities in an optimal manner. Such solutions help organize the location and space dynamics for offices, commercial and industrial buildings. Some of these also include features to schedule meetings, log-in visitors, security &amp; safety, computerized maintenance management software (CMMC), computerized asset and facility management (CAFM).</div><div>BMS (Building Management Systems): These are systems built to manage building’s electrical and mechanical equipment such as ventilation, lighting, power systems, fire systems, security systems and other for managing building performance efficiently.</div><div>Property listing portals (aggregators): These were the first set of fully online-portal based solution. They are essentially digital yellow pages glorified with audio-visual enhancements with property images, floor plans, maps and other specifications information. They do not enable direct interaction with the seller or builder. They lack any transaction processing or service processing features. They are also limited in their revenue generation model as listing and lead generation services.</div></div><div>This opens up an opportunity to create something unique that is comprehensive and cohesive to the address the challenges posed by increasing population and complex resource management, opportunities of urbanization and digitalization and benefits of emerging economies striving to try new unique solutions to innovate and simplify.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Need for Digitalization and Urbanization in Real Estate</title><description><![CDATA[2015 saw a new trend in global economy. It’s been seven years since the Global Financial Crisis (GFC) that brought attention to loosen monetary policies in US, Europe and Japan characterized by quantitative easing and reduced interest rates. At the same time, emerging market economies have expanded, thus opening doors for new business opportunities. This has been characterized by the following further changes: China’s impact on global trade and economicsInterest rate volatility has made business<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_0a336d5251e144a88838986c305257b0%7Emv2.png/v1/fill/w_389%2Ch_439/577c7f_0a336d5251e144a88838986c305257b0%7Emv2.png"/>]]></description><dc:creator>Avadhesh Gupta | Founder, CEO | REALEX APP</dc:creator><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2017/05/29/Need-for-Digitalization-and-Urbanization-in-Real-Estate</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2017/05/29/Need-for-Digitalization-and-Urbanization-in-Real-Estate</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2017 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>2015 saw a new trend in global economy. It’s been seven years since the Global Financial Crisis (GFC) that brought attention to loosen monetary policies in US, Europe and Japan characterized by quantitative easing and reduced interest rates. At the same time, emerging market economies have expanded, thus opening doors for new business opportunities. This has been characterized by the following further changes:</div><div>China’s impact on global trade and economicsInterest rate volatility has made business look for outside creditIncreased scrutiny on lending and real estate mortgagesSurge in investor appetite for real estate related funds from 43% in 2013 to 54%</div><div>The backdrop to all these changes meant increasing capital inflow into real estate from pension funds and sovereign wealth funds. This involved increasing focus of private equity firms in emerging markets in Asia, India and Middle East. This also added necessity to increase the yield on real estate investments from 3.9% to 5% on average by improving business process, building process and IT systems.</div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_0a336d5251e144a88838986c305257b0~mv2.png"/><div>With the increasing amount of investments in urbanization and creating cities to accommodate the growing population and work-force, it is understood that the requirements for creating smart and sustainable buildings will go up. Effective infrastructure planning and sound investments will make future cities competitive and resilient.</div><div>In 2014 World’s 750 biggest cities account for 57% of GDP. By 2030, they will grow to 61% OR USD 80tn.</div><div>Urbanization will require USD 60–70tn investment over 2012-2030. Under current condition only USD 45tn is likely to be realized. USD 8tn worth of new infrastructure capacity by 2030.</div><div>On average Fortune 1000 companies miss their capital plans target for real estate by USD 12.2bn yearly. This allows for looking across alternative industry in infrastructure sector and across strategic groups within real estate industry – paving the way for success of RealexApp as a blue ocean strategy.</div><div>Almost 80% of the companies across industries are facing changes in customers buying and consumption patterns due to online and digital channels. Consumers spending via mobile will increase from USD 204bn in 2014 to USD 626bn by 2018. This will redefine the industry buyer group and allow for blue ocean to evolve.Businesses are failing to use almost 80% of customer data now generated.</div><div>By 2020 more than 50% of workforce will be Generation Y and Z members – and they have grown up connected, collaborative and mobile and will generate between 5x-8x more data than today. This will allow for RealexApp to apply blue ocean to create alternative and complementary services based on the data generated and used by the millennial.</div><div>ICT-enabled solution offers the potential to reduce annual emissions by an estimated 9.1 gig tons of greenhouse gases by 2020 which represent 16.5% of the projected total by 2020. This allows real estate to participate in blue ocean shift by shaping external trends on sustainable and renewable solutions over time.</div><div>Entrepreneurship is rising across the world and 600 of top entrepreneurs of the year outperformed ROA (return on Assets) with 16.8% Vs. 7.1% of that from S&amp;P 500 companies in 2012. This shows that the new breed of entrepreneurs is creating blue oceans by re-thinking the functional and emotional orientation of the industry.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Blockchain in Real Estate</title><description><![CDATA[Today, as computer-based property recording systems are prevalent in our cities but roll out at a snail’s pace in rural areas (often hindered by strained municipal budgets), and e-signatures are little used (due to legitimate fears of fraud), arguably the real estate closing process has lagged in its use of computer aided technology. Yet other aspects of real estate ownership have been transformed by the internet: smart home technology to remotely control heating and lighting and monitor<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/df74ddf71e7f4fc792c2382349f3f9ee.jpg"/>]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2017/04/29/Blockchain-in-Real-Estate</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2017/04/29/Blockchain-in-Real-Estate</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2017 14:20:01 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/df74ddf71e7f4fc792c2382349f3f9ee.jpg"/><div>Today, as computer-based property recording systems are prevalent in our cities but roll out at a snail’s pace in rural areas (often hindered by strained municipal budgets), and e-signatures are little used (due to legitimate fears of fraud), arguably the real estate closing process has lagged in its use of computer aided technology. Yet other aspects of real estate ownership have been transformed by the internet: smart home technology to remotely control heating and lighting and monitor security;</div><div>Now add to our brave new world blockchain, a cloud-based decentralized ledger system that could offer speed, economy and improved security for real estate transactions. Will the real estate transaction industry avoid or embrace it? What is blockchain? Blockchain is best-known as the technology behind bitcoin, however bitcoin is not blockchain. Bitcoin is an implementation of blockchain technology. Blockchain is a data structure that allows for a digital ledger of transactions to be shared among a distributed network of computers. It uses cryptography to allow each participant on the network to manipulate the ledger in a secure way without the need for a central authority such as a bank or trade association. Using algorithms, the system can verify if a transaction will be approved and added to the blockchain and once it is on the blockchain it is extremely difficult to change or remove that transaction. A blockchain can be an open system or a system restricted to permissive users. There can be private blockchains (for ownership records or business transactions, for instance) and public blockchains (for public municipal data, real estate records etc.). Funds can be transferred by wires automatically authorized by the blockchain or via bitcoin or other virtual currency. Transparent, secure, frictionless payment is touted as one of blockchain’s many benefits. How does a blockchain differ from a record kept by a financing institution or a government agency? In a blockchain, there is no third-party intermediary verifying the veracity of the transaction. Rather it is verified by “nodes.” A “node” is a transaction between computers. Each node contains the history of a transaction down to the “genesis block” or beginning block. Once a command is made to execute a transaction, the node will trace through the history of the blockchain all the way to the genesis block to confirm that the new transacting party is “cleared” to join the block. The new block can then be added to the chain, which creates an indelible and transparent record of transactions. How is a blockchain transaction more secure than any other transaction? In theory, blockchain is tamper-proof because it is decentralized and not controlled by one party. All the nodes maintaining the same database will be involved in verifying the transaction which is a check on the veracity of the system. The system is analogous to creating a unique digital fingerprint (or “hash”) for each transaction that is stored in the database by each member of the blockchain. The hash is validated by algorithms and only can be changed if the utilized consensus mechanism verifies that the transaction is legitimate. This assures secure and authenticated transactions. Is blockchain inviolable? Time will tell.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Big data in real estate: too big to ignore</title><description><![CDATA[Since the beginning of 2015, there are clear signs that big data will grow in importance in the real estate sector. There are developments, newcomers and large investors which propel the use and capabilities of data in the sector. Moreover, sophisticated data modelling and analytics are increasingly being used to support smart environmental reporting compliance and support productivity. We believe that 2017 will be the year that data analytics will have its final breakthrough in real estate.]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2017/01/30/Big-data-in-real-estate-too-big-to-ignore</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2017/01/30/Big-data-in-real-estate-too-big-to-ignore</guid><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_3c1e6f213258490580b99db162a7cb31~mv2_d_2800_2283_s_2.jpg"/></div><div>Since the beginning of 2015, there are clear signs that big data will grow in importance in the real estate sector. There are developments, newcomers and large investors which propel the use and capabilities of data in the sector. Moreover, sophisticated data modelling and analytics are increasingly being used to support smart environmental reporting compliance and support productivity. We believe that 2017 will be the year that data analytics will have its final breakthrough in real estate. Regarding retrieving up-to-date information and better decision making, some commercial real estate parties are already using number crunching from public and private data sources. Big data platforms are capable of processing large public and licensed data sources to analyze a building’s structure, building year and whether it is renovated recently, as well as the financial status of the owner and occupier. </div><div>Fundamental changes in corporate thinking</div><div>However, big data causes not only major changes in the real estate transactions market, it will also have a major impact in the user market. Pressure to measure performance is constantly growing. Gathering big data such as non-financial metrics will lead to fundamental changes in corporate thinking about the impact of real estate. But gathering the right data is not easy, and even harder is making effective use of it to support strategic decision making. Emerging trends such as corporate social responsibility and minimum efficiency standards are placing increasing pressure on investors and owners of commercial real estate to gather more data. This will lead to an integration of non-financial metrics into companies’ building practices to demonstrate organizational performance more comprehensively.</div><div>The rise of connected buildings</div><div>A huge development in this field is the rise of connected buildings. These smart buildings have sensors to measure aspects such as air quality and energy consumption through the whole building. This gives office users and owners better insight into the current use of the building. Besides the physical aspects, it can also give insight into where employees are and use of space. In this relatively new area of measurement, collecting and understanding data that relates organizational outcomes back to physical features of buildings, and more importantly acting on this information will put companies at an advantage.</div><div>As stated, it seems that big data is working on an inexorable rise. Both leading commercial real estate companies as leading corporations are already using big data in real estate; in 2017 it will move further into mainstream.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>India's top 10 real estate policy reforms of 2016</title><description><![CDATA[2016 has been a year of transition for the real estate sector, with several policy initiatives aimed at making the sector more organized, formal and mature. While many policies were made to facilitate the Prime Minister’s flagship project of providing ‘Housing for All by 2022’, others focused on making the sector more transparent and organized. Here’s the list of the top 10 policy reforms of 2016 that impacted the realestate sector and are sure to have a spillover effect in 2017 as well:1) Real<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_2ace2e2aefc548e3803dc6a85bdc2ec9.jpg"/>]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/12/21/Indias-top-10-real-estate-policy-reforms-of-2016</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/12/21/Indias-top-10-real-estate-policy-reforms-of-2016</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 10:14:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>2016 has been a year of transition for the real estate sector, with several policy initiatives aimed at making the sector more organized, formal and mature. While many policies were made to facilitate the Prime Minister’s flagship project of providing ‘Housing for All by 2022’, others focused on making the sector more transparent and organized. Here’s the list of the top 10 policy reforms of 2016 that impacted the realestate sector and are sure to have a spillover effect in 2017 as well:</div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_2ace2e2aefc548e3803dc6a85bdc2ec9.jpg"/><div>1) Real Estate Regulatory Act</div><div>The Real Estate (Regulation and Developent) Act, 2016 which came into force in March 2016 has laid down a regulatory framweork which is set to change the way real estate sector operates in India. It aims to enhance transparency, bring greater accountability, set disclousre norms to protect the interest of all stakeholders and also ensure speedy execution of property disputes in due course.</div><div>2) Benami Transactions Act</div><div>The Benami Transactions (Prohibition) Amendment Act, 2016 lays down stringent rules and penalties associated with dealings related to &quot;benami&quot; transactions. It establishes a regulatory mechanism to deal with disputes arising with such transactions and levying penalties as needed to increase the institution investor participation and regulating the sector with an aim to make India an attractive investment destination.</div><div>3) Boost to affordable housing construction</div><div>In a bid to promote affordable housing, the Honourable Finance Minister proposed 100% deduction in profits to an undertaking from a housing project for flats up to 30 sq meters in four metro cities and 60 sq meters in other cities which are approved during June 2016 to March 2019. Another condition was that the project should be completed within three years of grant of approval.</div><div>4) Interest subsidy to home buyers</div><div>To stimulate housing demand from first- time home buyers, the Union Budget 2016-17 also proposed deduction of addition interest of INR 50,000 per annum for first time home buyers for loans up to INR 35 lakhs sanctioned during the next financial year for houses with a value not exceeding INR 50 lakhs. This move should positively influence home sales in non-metros in the long term where residential product prices are not as skyrocketing as in the metros.</div><div>5) Change in arbitration norms</div><div>Change in arbitration norms for construction companies specifies release of 75% of the amount against margin free guarantees in cases where arbitral awards have been given but contested which should improve the cash flow position of large developers who have significant exposure in infrastructure and government contracts and eventually help in speedy execution of large infrastructure projects. Coming at a time when most developers are struggling with liquidity issues, this is a boon from an overall perspective.</div><div>6) Service tax exemption</div><div>Exemption of service tax on construction of affordable houses up to 60 square meters under any scheme of the Central or State Government including PPP schemes will further propel construction in affordable segment across India and encourage greater collaboration between the public and private sector as well as participation in affordable home construction.</div><div>7) DDT exemption</div><div>The Union Budget 2016-17 exempted any distribution made out of the income of the Special Purpose Vehicles (SPVs) to the Real Estate Investment Trusts (REIT) and Infrastructure Investment Trusts (InvIT) from the levy of Dividend Distribution Tax. This paved the way for the REIT model to become financially viable for retail investors.</div><div>8) Goods and Services Tax</div><div>Goods and Services Tax (GST) is a positive move towards simplification of Indian tax system. However, the real estate industry is still awaiting clarity on which items fall into &quot;sin&quot; and &quot;common use&quot; and whether they will attract 18%, or 12% possible tax rates. Additional clarification is also needed if the implementation of GST will subsume existing service tax and value added tax (VAT) which are levied for under construction projects currently.</div><div>9) Demonetization</div><div>The recent demonetization of INR 500 and INR 1,000 rupee notes by Honourable Prime Minister is perceived as a significant reform. In the long run, this measure along with Real Estate (Regulation and Development) Act, 2016 (RERA) will align the real estate sector to the international standards of doing business resulting in more fund flow from institutional investors, banks and higher unit sales.</div><div>10) PR for foreign investors</div><div>The Union Cabinet approved the grant of Permanent Residency Status (PRS) to foreign investors subject to various conditions and with a provision for renewal for another 10 years. As PRS allows the holders' spouse/dependents to take up employment in India as well as the purchase of one residential property for end-use, the end user pool, mainly for high-end and luxury segment products stands increased which can promote the asset class in a big way.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>US (under Trump) to continue on the MoU for development of three Smart city projects in India - Allahabad, Ajmer &amp; Vishakhapatnam</title><description><![CDATA[The new administration under President-elect Donald Trump will continue to engage with India on development of smart cities, a US government official told ET. India and the United States, during President Barack Obama’s term, signed memorandums of understanding to develop three smart cities in Allahabad, Ajmer and Visakhapatnam. The US agreed to assist the cities in project planning, infrastructure development, feasibility studies and capacity building. “We had initial discussions with the]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/12/21/US-under-Donald-Trump-to-continue-on-the-MoU-for-development-of-three-Smart-city-projects-in-India---Allahabad-Ajmer-Vishakhapatnam</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/12/21/US-under-Donald-Trump-to-continue-on-the-MoU-for-development-of-three-Smart-city-projects-in-India---Allahabad-Ajmer-Vishakhapatnam</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 06:10:15 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>The new administration under President-elect Donald Trump will continue to engage with India on development of smart cities, a US government official told ET. India and the United States, during President Barack Obama’s term, signed memorandums of understanding to develop three smart cities in Allahabad, Ajmer and Visakhapatnam. The US agreed to assist the cities in project planning, infrastructure development, feasibility studies and capacity building. “We had initial discussions with the transition team (under new Presidency). It is still early stages but we have shared our plans and they have been included,” said Vinay Vijay Singh, deputy assistant secretary in the US Department of Commerce. Singh said there are some challenges from the Indian side which can be addressed. “Indian cities should be enabled to have more autonomy,” he said. The mechanics between the Centre and states in India need to be worked out, Singh said. “I know they are working hard at it. We had this (smart cities) competition and the money has gone to the states, then we go to the states and some states say we don’t have the money because these things haven’t been done,” he said. Some companies which are already involved in India’s smart cities project also echoed these concerns. Ashley O’Connor, vice president, Region Business Line leader, AECOM, said that some clarity would be welcome. “In Vizag (Visakhapatnam), in particular, there were talks of a new airport. It would need significant investment, so clarity around these, what is in works and how are they working forward would be helpful for the business side,” she said. Singh said that US participation in development of smart cities in India is not a political initiative and the agenda is driven by the US private sector, which sees this as a growth area. “We will continue to engage with all stakeholders. We will also work with multilateral institutions to help eliminate the initial risk involved in such projects,” Singh said, citing the example of US government’s Department of Treasury’s initiative with Pune Municipal Corporation to help the city raise funds via issuance of bonds. Devin Hampton, chief of staff for US Trade &amp; Development Agency, said the focus areas for smart cities are in energy, telecom and transportation sector. “We will help identify opportunities and it is important that there should be more cities to cities contact for greater synergy on best practices,” Hampton said. A special cell in India on US investments similar to that of Japan may also help, he said.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Canada, India and UAE in the top ten for 2016 rankings of LEED Certified buildings</title><description><![CDATA[India ranks third in US Green Building Council's annual ranking of the top 10 countries for Leadership in Energy & Environmental Design (LEED) certified buildings. The country had around 15.90 million gross square meters (GSM) of LEED-certified space and an additional 89.28 million cumulative GSM of LEED-certified and -registered space, totalling 2,386 projects participating in LEED across the country. “With a focus on LEED and green buildings, India is prioritizing environmental and human]]></description><dc:creator>Economic Times</dc:creator><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/12/20/Canada-India-and-UAE-in-the-top-ten-for-2016-rankings-of-LEED-Certified-buildings</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/12/20/Canada-India-and-UAE-in-the-top-ten-for-2016-rankings-of-LEED-Certified-buildings</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 05:53:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>India ranks third in US Green Building Council's annual ranking of the top 10 countries for Leadership in Energy &amp; Environmental Design (LEED) certified buildings. The country had around 15.90 million gross square meters (GSM) of LEED-certified space and an additional 89.28 million cumulative GSM of LEED-certified and -registered space, totalling 2,386 projects participating in LEED across the country. “With a focus on LEED and green buildings, India is prioritizing environmental and human health in the built environment on a holistic scale and helping us get one step closer to a green building for all within this generation,” said Mahesh Ramanujam, president and chief executive officer of USGBC. LEED is the world’s most widely used and recognized green building rating system. The top 10 list highlights countries outside of the United States that are making significant strides in sustainable building design, construction and operations. India is part of a growing international trend as global green building is expected to double every three years, according to a Dodge Data &amp; Analytics World Green Building Trends 2016 SmartMarket Report, to which USGBC was a contributing partner. China topped the 2016 rankings, with 34.62 million GSM, followed by Canada, India, Brazil, Republic of Korea, Taiwan, Germany, Turkey, Sweden and United Arab Emirates. Emerging economies will continue to be engines of green growth, with development varying from twofold to sixfold over current green building levels. &quot;Increased consumer demand has also pushed the world’s green building market to a trillion-dollar industry, a surge that has led to a corresponding increase in the scope and size of the green building materials market, which is expected to reach $234 billion by 2019,&quot; according to the report that was conducted acorss 70 countries. At present, there are more than 82,000 commercial projects participating in LEED, totalling more than 1.4 billion GSM of space worldwide with an additional 112,000 residential units that have been certified under LEED homes. An estimated 170,000 GSM of space achieves LEED certification every day in more than 162 countries and territories across the globe.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The pros &amp; cons of India's currency ban (demonetization) on real estate sector</title><description><![CDATA[The Indian government's decision to ban Rs 500 and Rs 1,000 currency notes is expected to hit the real estate sector hardest. As a sector that's known for menace of black money, real estate is now likely to move towards improved transparency. The decision would impact the real estate sector in several ways; both positively and negatively: Take a look:Positives:1) Going forward, developers would be forced to conduct transactions in white money as the cash component usually involved in buying and<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_7245aa21e3cd4d5289b341fde1c88e1f%7Emv2_d_3000_2109_s_2.jpg"/>]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/11/30/The-pros-cons-of-Indias-currency-ban-demonetization-on-real-estate-sector</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/11/30/The-pros-cons-of-Indias-currency-ban-demonetization-on-real-estate-sector</guid><pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 06:18:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>The Indian government's decision to ban Rs 500 and Rs 1,000 currency notes is expected to hit the real estate sector hardest. As a sector that's known for menace of black money, real estate is now likely to move towards improved transparency. The decision would impact the real estate sector in several ways; both positively and negatively: Take a look:</div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_7245aa21e3cd4d5289b341fde1c88e1f~mv2_d_3000_2109_s_2.jpg"/><div>Positives:</div><div>1) Going forward, developers would be forced to conduct transactions in white money as the cash component usually involved in buying and selling has been eliminated. This would give much comfort to lenders and investors as it would weed out unaccounted cash flows from the system.</div><div>2) Land acquisition quite often involved a significant portion of black money. Thus it is expected that land prices would fall gradually which would thereby bring down unit prices. It will ultimately benefit the end user and expectantly improve sales velocity and at the same time address the affordability issue the sector has been facing.</div><div>3) Demand in the affordable housing sector will not be impacted. Cash component in affordable sector is typically minimal as buyers require home loans for up to 90% of the property price.</div><div>4) The primary market which is largely driven by large developers is unlikely to get affected that much as most large and reputed developers already do not deal with cash transactions.</div><div>5) This measures to curb black money will further increase transparency and credibility in the sector, at a time when the setting up of a Real Estate Regulatory Authority (RERA) in each state is set to bring in increased accountability in the markets.</div><div>6) Institutional funding to developers which till present day came with a higher risk weightage is bound to see some softening with the increased transparency</div><div>Negatives:</div><div>1) Developers with sizeable land parcels will face difficulty due to the significant markdown in market valuations of their land banks.</div><div>2) It's a move towards eradication of corruption and bribery in the sector, particularly while obtaining approvals. However, delays in approvals can be expected as the authorities are used to receiving cash to fast track the process.</div><div>3) In the immediate future, the sector will be under serious pressure with volume and number of transactions in residential and land markets seeing a substantial downward trend.</div><div>4) We are also likely to see an impact on general liquidity in the market and therefore working capital needs for small and medium developers and other businesses will be lot higher in the short term</div><div>5) Of the property markets, Delhi-National Capital Region is likely to witness a hard landing as the market is known for highest involvement of cash component.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Benefits of India's GST reform</title><description><![CDATA[In a historic development, the Rajya Sabha passed the constitutional amendment paving the way for the goods & services tax (GST). The reform is expected to bump up GDP by about a percentage point or even more.Here's a look at GST's benefits.1. Life gets simplerGST will replace 17 indirect tax levies and compliance costs will fall.2. Revenue will get a boostEvasion set to drop.Input tax credit will encourage suppliers to pay taxes. States and Centre will have dual oversight. The number of tax<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_2776ffe8a0c44e8cab44eb93dd75b9f6%7Emv2_d_3680_2453_s_4_2.jpg"/>]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/10/05/Benefits-of-Indias-GST-reform</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/10/05/Benefits-of-Indias-GST-reform</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 07:26:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>In a historic development, the Rajya Sabha passed the constitutional amendment paving the way for the goods &amp; services tax (GST). The reform is expected to bump up GDP by about a percentage point or even more.</div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_2776ffe8a0c44e8cab44eb93dd75b9f6~mv2_d_3680_2453_s_4_2.jpg"/><div>Here's a look at GST's benefits.</div><div>1. Life gets simpler</div><div>GST will replace 17 indirect tax levies and compliance costs will fall.</div><div>2. Revenue will get a boost</div><div>Evasion set to drop.Input tax credit will encourage suppliers to pay taxes. States and Centre will have dual oversight. The number of tax exempt goods will decline.</div><div>3. A common market</div><div>It's currently fragmented along state lines, pushing costs up 20-30%.</div><div>4. Logistics, Inventory costs will fall</div><div>Checks at state borders slow movement of trucks. In India, they travel 280 km a day compared with 800 km in the US.</div><div>5. Investment boost</div><div>For many capital goods, input tax credit is not available. Full input tax credit under GST will mean a 12-14% drop in the cost of capital goods. Expected: A 6% rise in capital goods investment, 2% overall.</div><div>6. Make in India</div><div>Manufacturing will get more competitive as GST addresses cascading of tax, inter-state tax, high logistics costs and fragmented market. Increased protection from imports as GST provides for appropriate countervailing duty.</div><div>7. Less developed states get a lift</div><div>The current 2% inter-state levy means production is kept within a state. Under the GST national market, this can be dispersed, creating opportunities for others.</div><div>8. Manufactured goods could become cheaper</div><div>Lower logistics and tax costs.</div><div>9. GDP Lift</div><div>HSBC estimates an 80 basis point rise in GDP growth over 3-5 years. NCAER pegs this at 0.9-1.7% thanks to the elimination of tax cascading.</div><div>10. Freeing up online</div><div>State restrictions and levies have complicated ecommerce. Some sellers do not even ship to particular states. All this will end with GST.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Smart cities: The smart person's guide to how rapid urbanization is leading to smarter cities that improve the lives of citizens through technology</title><description><![CDATA[As the world becomes increasingly more urban, with 60% of its population forecast to live in cities by 2050, cities are becoming more technologically advanced. This type of city is known as a smart city and the goal is to improve the quality of the lives of citizens through better communication and the services offered while reducing overall costs.Executive summary What it is: A smart city uses IoT sensors and technology to connect components across a city to derive data and improve the lives of]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/09/18/Smart-cities-The-smart-persons-guide-Rapid-urbanization-is-leading-to-smarter-cities-that-improve-the-lives-of-citizens-through-technology-This-comprehensive-guide-details-the-important-aspects-of-a-smart-city</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/09/18/Smart-cities-The-smart-persons-guide-Rapid-urbanization-is-leading-to-smarter-cities-that-improve-the-lives-of-citizens-through-technology-This-comprehensive-guide-details-the-important-aspects-of-a-smart-city</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2016 08:43:36 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>As the world becomes increasingly more urban, with 60% of its population forecast to live in cities by 2050, cities are becoming more technologically advanced. This type of city is known as a smart city and the goal is to improve the quality of the lives of citizens through better communication and the services offered while reducing overall costs.</div><div>Executive summary</div><div>What it is: A smart city uses IoT sensors and technology to connect components across a city to derive data and improve the lives of citizens and visitors.What it does: Oftentimes, a mobile app is provided to give immediate access to data, communication channels and more, so that people can do everything from avoiding traffic jams, to finding a parking spot, reporting a pot hole, or an overflowing dumpster.Why it matters: The world is becoming more urbanized, and by 2050, more than 60% of the world's population is expected to live in cities. Making these cities better places to live is essential to quality of life by making them more sustainable and efficient with streamlined services.Who it affects: It affects everyone on the planet.When is this happening: This is happening now.Where is this happening: Early adopters of smart city technology were European cities, but U.S. cities have quickly picked up steam and are incorporating technology into municipal infrastructure.Who is making it happen: Public and private companies, as well as federal, state and city government are getting involved to make it easier for municipalities to adopt new technology.How to get it: Citizens can form a grassroots campaign to get support and ask government officials to incorporate more technology into their city.</div><div>What it is</div><div>There is a range of definitions of a smart city, but the consensus is that smart cities utilize IoT sensors, actuators and technology to connect components across the city. This connects every layer of a city, from the air to the street to underground. It's when you can derive data from everything that is connected and utilize it to improve the lives of citizens and improve communication between citizens and the government that a city becomes a smart city, said Esmeralda Swartz, head of strategy and marketing of the software business unit for Ericsson.</div><div>Gartner analyst Bettina Tratz-Ryan said, &quot;Our definition of smart cities is around how you become efficient at optimizing certain technologies or operations or infrastructures. How you can start to share outcome or best practices with each other and generate not just best practices but generate citizen outcome or context. The contextual services where you don't only look at a citizen but you look at a person with individual needs or business groups with very specific needs. That constitutes a smart city.&quot;</div><div>What it does Smart cities improve the quality of the lives of citizens. They often employ a mobile app to give fast access to traffic information, road conditions and more.</div><div>&quot;The example I like to use is common services. If you think about one of the biggest drivers of traffic congestion, it is people, whether residents or visitors, driving around looking for an open parking spot. Now through a mobile app, through sensors that are deployed on parking spots, you know exactly where [to go] and you don't have to search around and try to find an open parking spot. It's those simple things we take for granted for improving interaction with common city services,&quot; Swartz said.</div><div>&quot;Another thing that drives the point home is smart waste management. Think about sensor technology applied to a smart waste receptacle. It knows when the trash is basically hitting the middle of the container. It compresses it down and when it gets to the top and is full, it notifies the city sanitation department that it's time to collect the trash,&quot; she said.</div><div>Additional resources:</div><div>Internet of Things World Forum: Pushing adoption of IoT business models How the White House 'Opportunity Project' wants to use open data to improve communities</div><div>Why it matters</div><div>The smart city industry is projected to be a $400 billion market by 2020, with 600 cities around the globe expected to generate 60% of the world's GDP by 2025, according to McKinsey research, as previously published in TechRepublic.</div><div>Urbanization is an issue that all cities have to deal with around the globe.</div><div>&quot;When you have more population coming in, there's a mass migration from the country to the city. The impact is similar to the urbanization that occurred during the industrial revolution,&quot; Swartz said. &quot;The best way to optimize that experience is digitally.</div><div>&quot;The questions that urban engineers are dealing with include, How do you take the opportunity with people armed with smart phones to deal with urbanization? How do you combine technology and ubiquitous mobility and an increasing voracious appetite on the part of city dwellers to have efficiency and how do they get services now and how do they really interact in a more fluid way with common city services?&quot;</div><div>Jarrett Wendt, vice president of strategic initiatives and business development for Panasonic Enterprise Solutions Company, said, &quot;You do it because you improve and impact people's lives. Period, end of story. This is about transforming people's lives into making them more efficient.&quot;</div><div>&quot;Quality of life is not spending three hours in a car every day. If you're becoming smarter and more connected and utilizing those city services that are available then you're alleviating some of those pain points,&quot; Wendt said.</div><div>Mrinalini Ingram, who spent 16 years at Cisco Systems working with smart and connected communities before becoming the new head of the Smart City initiative at Verizon in March, said, &quot;One of the most important reasons to have a smart city is that we can actually communicate with our environment in a way that we never have in the past.&quot;</div><div>&quot;With the smart city capability we are just touching on that higher wave of transition of people being able to communicate and interact with the environment around them. That could be physical assets that are around them, services that are available around them and the ability to not only get information but provide a two-way dialogue between an individual and their environment and the services that enable activities around that space,&quot; Ingram said.</div><div>Who it affects</div><div>This affects everyone, whether directly or indirectly. People who live in smart cities or who are visiting smart cities have the immediate benefit of being connected to the governing body for information and services. The quality of their lives can be improved with better traffic management, waste removal, snow removal and more. Those who don't live or visit a smart city are affected simply because of the lack of connected services and communication available to them.</div><div>A smart city also benefits the environment. Water and energy usage are sustainability issues, and a common thread across all smart city projects is how a city reduces CO2 emissions.</div><div>When this is happening</div><div>This is happening now.</div><div>&quot;It's the now generation. People say, 'I want access now. I want to understand how I can make my life more efficient.' That's what's driving not just smart cities but the reason why internet of things and connectivity why it's impacting all of these different industries. It's efficiencies. More contextual interactions. A better experience overall is the goal,&quot; Swartz said.</div><div>As reported in TechRepublic, the Internet of Things was already at a tipping point last year, with future growth happening at an explosive rate. Smart cities are part of the world of IoT, with everything from streetlights and parking spots digitally connected.</div><div>&quot;I think the evolution of this has been amazingly fast as far as a creation of an industry but people are still looking for that tangibility. Sometimes things are happening that are smart city activities but they're happening in pockets,&quot; Ingram said.</div><div>&quot;We're seeing a lot more pilots happening, you're seeing individual solutions happening on a broader scale. Lighting solutions are taking off faster than most. Security solutions and traffic solutions are very big. It really kind of comes down to a tagline I use quite a bit. That it's 'think big, start small and scale.' That is the approach that a lot of cities are taking and a lot of companies are taking where you have to have that overarching architectural approach and what that future vision will look like ultimately. But they have to start small. Let's do one neighborhood, let's do one venue, let's do one downtown strip and test out that solution and make sure it makes sense,&quot; Ingram said.</div><div>Where this is happening</div><div>Cities across the globe are becoming smarter. Early adopters were the European cities of Barcelona and Amsterdam, with Copenhagen, Dubai, Singapore, Hamburg, and Nice, France quickly following suit. In the U.S., San Francisco, Chicago, New York, Miami, Kansas City, Miami, Denver, Boston and Atlanta are among the cities adding smart city technologies and pilot programs, as reported in an in-depth TechRepublic article.</div><div>Who is making it happen</div><div>At the end of the day we can make all the greatest plans in the world, but if resources aren't available to implement them, it doesn't really matter.</div><div>Companies such as Intel, Cisco Systems, IBM, Verizon, Silver Spring Networks, Build.io, GE Lighting, Ericsson and Siemens are among those providing smart city solutions. Associations such as TM Forum, which is a leadership collaboration of seven cities created earlier this year to push the creation of smart cities around the globe, are also spurring development, as reported in TechRepublic. Last year, the Obama administration announced a new smart cities initiative to invest $160 in federal grants to create software and IoT applications to help local communities improve city services.</div><div>&quot;I'm looking forward to seeing a whole group of innovative new startups that you can already see being built up. The new wave of creativity that they are bringing to the table is enormously exciting,&quot; Ingram said.</div><div>&quot;We want to encourage that small entrepreneur or that student in the university to build an application or to build a service that fits the need of what they see every single day. That's a whole other industry that is just now beginning. That combined with the personal interactions are probably the two biggest positives around why we really are excited about smart cities,&quot; Ingram said.</div><div>How to get it</div><div>Many cities first embark on becoming connected through streetlights because they offer a quick revenue return for municipalities with the use of LED reduced energy lighting.</div><div>&quot;We had a project in L.A. that was a partnership with Phillips that was basically smart lighting. These light posts that could be used for both energy reduction and LED's and when you save costs on these common city services using technology, imagine the impact of applying that budget to schools or other services that are increasingly under budget constraints,&quot; Swartz said.</div><div>Utilities and renewable energy are an optional starting point, by offering alternative energy options. And public safety is another way to drive the use of technology by offering connected emergency response services.</div><div>TM Forum is hoping to unite more than 100 cities in the development of smart cities, including those without the resources to add smart innovation. The forum will work to develop recommendations on how those cities can work within urban incubators and learn things such as how to structure a partnership within the private sector to create opportunities for innovation.</div><div>Atlanta is one of the cities embarking on a smart city initiative. Atlanta CIO and commissioner Samir Saini said that he hopes the lessons learned in Atlanta will benefit other cities, especially those without the necessary resources readily available.</div><div>&quot;At the end of the day we can make all the greatest plans in the world, but if resources aren't available to implement them, it doesn't really matter,&quot; Saini said.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>GST in India: Real Estate Industry Voices Thoughts</title><description><![CDATA[The Indian Parliament has finally unanimously passed the constitution amendment Bill to roll out Goods & Services Tax (GST). While the Rajya Sabha passed the changes to the Constitution (22nd Amendment) Bill, 2014 on August 3, 2016, the Lok Sabha cleared the bill on August 8, 2016. GST is set to replace as many as 17 indirect taxes levied by states and the Centre, from April 1, 2017. At least 16 out of 31 provinces with Assemblies (29 states and two of the seven union territories), or more than<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_224d44ce9fa44b57ace4245526e23a4e%7Emv2.jpg"/>]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/08/09/GST-in-India-Real-Estate-Industry-Voices-Thoughts</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/08/09/GST-in-India-Real-Estate-Industry-Voices-Thoughts</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 07:20:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_224d44ce9fa44b57ace4245526e23a4e~mv2.jpg"/><div>The Indian Parliament has finally unanimously passed the constitution amendment Bill to roll out Goods &amp; Services Tax (GST). While the Rajya Sabha passed the changes to the Constitution (22nd Amendment) Bill, 2014 on August 3, 2016, the Lok Sabha cleared the bill on August 8, 2016. GST is set to replace as many as 17 indirect taxes levied by states and the Centre, from April 1, 2017. At least 16 out of 31 provinces with Assemblies (29 states and two of the seven union territories), or more than half the total, need to pass this Bill before it can be sent for President's assent.</div><div>While some say the new tax system is expected to make manufacturing more competitive and speed up logistics, others claims it will add up to 2% to the country's GDP.</div><div>Here's what the top real estate developers and property consultants have to say:</div><div>Getamber Anand, National President, CREDAI and CMD, ATS Infrastructure</div><div>It could reduce harassment that is there due to multiple taxes today. But builders and consultants are concerned about a clause in the GST bill which says input tax credit shall not be available in respect of the goods and/or services acquired by the principal in the execution of works contract when such contract results in construction of immovable property, other than plant and machinery.</div><div>Rajeev Talwar, CEO, DLF</div><div>With the various local taxes and the central sales tax getting subsumed in one tax, the multiplicity of taxes goes away and makes it easier to deal with authorities, which has been a big issue so far. Various levies will then get rationalised which would result in more transparent taxation. This would also mean rationalisation of property prices in favour of the consumer.</div><div>Niranjan Hiranandani, Founder &amp; MD, Hiranandani Group</div><div>This is a major reform undertaken by the Modi government and it will be impacting the economy positively. If managed well, this alone has potential to add at least 1% to India's GDP growth. Capping the rate of tax is good. However, if the rate is increased later then it will prove to be tricky . Duality of tax authorities at state and central level is not a happy situation. If the states continue to levy stamp duty, other local taxes like labor cess and municipal taxes then it will add burden to home-buyers' cost.</div><div>Brotin Banerjee, MD &amp; CEO, Tata Housing</div><div>The Goods and Services Tax is likely to be a game changer for the real estate industry, which is currently facing issues of multiple taxation amounting to over 25 percent in indirect taxes. With the uniform tax, developers will have free input credits on GST paid for services and goods purchased by them which will reduce cost and can be passed as reduction to buyers. It will benefit real estate sector by ensuring a uniform tax structure and improve tax compliance by developers. It looks at bringing in greater transparency for the sector and may minimize unscrupulous transactions. GST will have a cascading effect for the homebuyers, as developers with more margins in their hands will be able to restructure the cost of the products in favour of consumers.</div><div>Parveen Jain, President, NAREDCO</div><div>The enactment of this law will single-handedly solve many of the challenges faced by the real estate sector and help in pulling the sluggish sector out of its long slumber. Heavy taxes that are being paid currently by the developers will automatically go down by a considerable percentage. Construction costs would be reduced to some extent and this benefit could be passed on to the customers, thereby triggering transactions in home buying. There would also be a positive impact on the commercial property segment, as commercial real estate which is already starving from funds could see some kind of a revival.</div><div>Vineet Relia, Managing Director, SARE Homes</div><div>The implementation of GST is likely to improve transparency and reduce tax evasion on account of better enforcement and compliance. The home buyer in general could benefit from the introduction of GST if the rates are moderate. The fact that works contract would be taxed as a service under the model GST law is a welcome move and is expected to provide certainty on taxability of the construction sector. This should lead to reduction in tax costs as the tax would be now charged on the actual contractual base and there would not be any overlap of VAT and service tax on a certain portion of such contracts like under the current regime. However, for the developer, the aspect of valuation is a matter of concern as currently no deduction is provided under GST for value of land. This can contribute to higher tax burden considering that there is already an additional tax incidence in the form of Stamp duty on value of land.</div><div>Manoj Gaur, President CREDAI-NCR &amp; MD, Gaursons India Ltd.</div><div>A well-defined GST implemented for the country will bring about a relief for this sector and its customers. Commercial realty players will be hugely benefited as all the lost Cenvat credit, which is in current regime a cost to commercial developer can be availed if GST is applied in a free flow manner that will also help in reducing costs. A much simplified single tax rate, reduced construction costs and better transparency in the sector will be much welcomed by the developers and its customers.</div><div>Shishir Baijal, Chairman &amp; Managing Director, Knight Frank India</div><div>For the real estate sector, the GST will streamline the domestic supply chain that will lead to a consolidated and efficient warehousing infrastructure in the country. This will give the much needed push to the retail and industrial sectors to grow. The positive sentiments after the passage of the GST bill will receive a further boost if RBI does its bit in reducing policy rates on the back of a good monsoon and controlled retail inflation in the economy.</div><div>Anshul Jain, Managing Director, India, Cushman &amp; Wakefield</div><div>The bill would benefit the overall real estate sector by ensuring a uniform tax structure, thereby improving the tax compliance by the developers. The GST Bill would replace most indirect taxes that currently exist, with one tax, thereby ensuring an efficient taxation system. Under GST, developers would see lesser burden of tax on input items like cement, steel, etc., as tax credits would be available for set off at various stages. This can lead to lower construction costs for developers across all asset classes, which could likely be passed on to property buyers / occupiers. However, the magnitude of impact of GST on the sector would hinge upon the final rate of GST decided by the government and more importantly on the actual implementation.</div><div>Anshuman Magazine, Chairman, CBRE - India and South East Asia</div><div>Once implemented, it is likely to have a positive impact on the real estate sector, which has linkages with over 250 ancillary industries. Unified taxation will also infuse the much needed transparency into our taxation system. While the complete effects of this bill will take some time to be realized in some sectors, overall, it is expected to have a long lasting and progressive impact on the economy, enhancing the prevalent business sentiment in the country.</div><div>Anuj Puri, Chairman &amp; Country Head, JLL India</div><div>In terms of cost reduction for manufacturers, the current tax structure has three layers at the central, state and city-levels, manufacturing units have to shell out a good amount of money to transport their goods. They end up paying multiple taxes on the transportation. Once GST is rolled out, there will be a common tax structure and thus, the burden of paying multiple taxes will go away. Such units will not have a varied tax structure for transportation of their goods to different locations and will not have to pay each time they transport goods, thus, reducing the overall cost. Likewise, there will be a cost reduction for logistics players, as logistics players create a stock transfer between inventory stocking points within states to avoid a multi-tax scenario. They have a large number of smaller warehouses at various locations amounting to more than 50 small warehouses in some cases, which increases the overall cost of logistics. Also, management of such small warehouses increases the cost and reduces the overall efficiency of the logistics players. With the implementation of GST, the tax burden will reduce and thus need to have such a fragmented warehouse system will decrease. The real estate sector also shares positive symbiotic relationships with more than 250 sectors such as cement, steel, IT, BFSI, etc. Due to this, the benefits or drawbacks of GST on each sector will also have an indirect impact on real estate and vice versa. At this point in time, we may see very limited tangible benefits on the real estate industry but the cascading effects will definitely be higher.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>RERA rules: 10 things to know about</title><description><![CDATA[RERA rules - The government has notified the final rules to implement the Real Estate (Regulation and Development) Act, 2016 (RERA). This aims to bring transparency and set accountability in the sector and help in completion of stalled projects. Here are the key points you should know about:Pay compensation1) Developers will now be required to refund or pay compensation to the allottees for delay in projects with an interest rate of the State Bank of India's highest marginal cost of lending rate<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_d53a7074d3a240ba8cbc06d728e5a82d%7Emv2.jpg"/>]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/07/15/RERA-rules-10-things-to-know-about</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/07/15/RERA-rules-10-things-to-know-about</guid><pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2016 07:30:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>RERA rules - The government has notified the final rules to implement the Real Estate (Regulation and Development) Act, 2016 (RERA). This aims to bring transparency and set accountability in the sector and help in completion of stalled projects. </div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_d53a7074d3a240ba8cbc06d728e5a82d~mv2.jpg"/><div> Here are the key points you should know about:</div><div>Pay compensation</div><div>1) Developers will now be required to refund or pay compensation to the allottees for delay in projects with an interest rate of the State Bank of India's highest marginal cost of lending rate plus 2% within 45 days of it becoming due. This would come to around 11% to 12%.</div><div>Deposit money</div><div>2) For the completion of ongoing projects, developers will have to deposit 70% of the amount collected and unused within three months of applying for registration of a project with the Real Estate Regulatory Authority in a separate bank account.</div><div>Punishment</div><div>3) The rules also contain clauses providing for compounding of punishment with imprisonment for violation of the orders of Real Estate Appellate Tribunal against payment of 10% of project cost in case of developers and 10% of the cost of property purchased in case of allottees and agents.</div><div>Sale of properties</div><div>4) Discrimination in sale of properties on any grounds will also not be entertained under the new rules. Adjudicating Officers, Real Estate Authorities and Appellate Tribunals shall dispose of complaints within 60 days.</div><div>Certification</div><div>5) In respect of the ongoing projects that have not received completion certificate in specified time, developers will have to make public the original sanctioned plans with specifications and changes made later, total amount collected from allottees, money used, original timeline for completion and the time period within which the developer undertakes to complete the project.</div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_0c81a19e56e640f6999e3add42511d73~mv2.png"/><div>Carpet area</div><div>6) Promoter shall also declare size of the apartment based on carpet area even if it was earlier sold on any other basis.</div><div>Registration</div><div>7) For registration of projects with the authorities, developers will be required to submit authenticated copy of PAN card, annual report comprising audited profit and loss account, balance sheet, cash flow statement and auditors report of the promoter for the immediate three preceding years, authenticated copy of legal title deed, copy of collaboration agreement if the promoter is not the owner of the plot. Promoter also has to declare information regarding the number of open and closed parking areas in the project.</div><div>Income Tax returns</div><div>8) The requirement of disclosing Income Tax returns proposed earlier has been withdrawn in the final Rules keeping in view the confidentiality attached with them and as pointed out by legal experts and promoters.</div><div>Fee for registration</div><div>9) To incentivize registration of projects and Real Estate Agents with Regulatory Authorities, fee for the same has been reduced by half based on suggestions from promoters for reduction of fee.</div><div>Information about details</div><div>10) To enable informed decisions by buyers, Real Estate Regulatory Authorities will ensure publication on their websites information relating to profile and track record of promoters, details of litigations, advertisement and prospectus issued about the project, details of apartments, plots and garages, registered agents and consultants, development plan, financial details of the promoters, status of approvals and projects etc.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Indian InvITs, REITs likely to be launched in 2017</title><description><![CDATA[The much-awaited Infrastructure Investment Trusts (InvITs) and Real Estate Investment Trusts (REITs) are likely to be launched in the country next year, says a study. "Currently, the market for REITs and InvITs is relatively nascent in the country. However, with various enabling factors such as the growth of the economy and the middle class, and a concomitant need for housing and infrastructure, the demand for these investment vehicles will see an upswing over the next few years," PwC<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_2309159f667542d58dce0327537c0f79%7Emv2.jpg"/>]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/06/16/InvITs-REITs-likely-to-be-launched-in-2017-Study</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/06/16/InvITs-REITs-likely-to-be-launched-in-2017-Study</guid><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 07:02:19 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_2309159f667542d58dce0327537c0f79~mv2.jpg"/><div>The much-awaited Infrastructure Investment Trusts (InvITs) and Real Estate Investment Trusts (REITs) are likely to be launched in the country next year, says a study.  &quot;Currently, the market for REITs and InvITs is relatively nascent in the country. However, with various enabling factors such as the growth of the economy and the middle class, and a concomitant need for housing and infrastructure, the demand for these investment vehicles will see an upswing over the next few years,&quot; PwC Partner-Tax Abhishek Goenka said in a statement.  He said the first InvIT is expected to be launched in March next year, while REITs by the end of 2017.  According to the PwC-APREA report, REITs market has evolved substantially in several countries and these investment vehicles have gained immensely in terms of their market capitalisation.  &quot;A primary condition for the growth of these markets, as demonstrated by the experience of different countries, is their ability to customise regulations governing these investment vehicles in conformity with domestic market conditions,&quot; Goenka added.  &quot;India has managed to achieve this to some extent and therefore, we will soon see REITs and InvITs launched here,&quot; he said.  In the near future, REITs are expected to increase the depth of the Indian property market through a sound regulatory framework which ensures transparency and high governance standards, and promotes regular monitoring of their performance, the statement said.  &quot;Given the importance of these two sectors in the country, and the paucity of public funds available to stimulate their growth, it is imperative that additional channels of financing are put in place.  &quot;REITs and InvITs can play a pivotal role here as these investment vehicles can be used to attract private investment in these sectors while relieving the burden on formal banking institutions,&quot; he said.  The report also discusses how the adoption of Ind AS (effective from April 1) is likely to have a significant impact on the financial statements of Indian companies across sectors, including real estate and construction.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Foreign real estate players bullish on India property market</title><description><![CDATA[Despite the slowdown in real market in India, foreign developers are still bullish on investing in Indian property market.Chinese property developer Dalian Wanda Group, signed a memorandum of understanding (MoU) earlier this year with the northern state of Haryana to develop 'Wanda Industrial New City'. The company is planning to invest $10 billion in the next ten years in India to construct industrial townships, retail and residential developments. The construction of the phase-I of 'Wanda<img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_1d54eec145ee4d17b1f30ee9feda6412%7Emv2.jpg"/>]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/06/15/Foreign-real-estate-players-bullish-on-India-property-market</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/06/15/Foreign-real-estate-players-bullish-on-India-property-market</guid><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2016 08:17:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>Despite the slowdown in real market in India, foreign developers are still bullish on investing in Indian property market.</div><div>Chinese property developer Dalian Wanda Group, signed a memorandum of understanding (MoU) earlier this year with the northern state of Haryana to develop 'Wanda Industrial New City'. The company is planning to invest $10 billion in the next ten years in India to construct industrial townships, retail and residential developments. The construction of the phase-I of 'Wanda Industrial New City' is likely to begin in 2016 and it will be spread over 1,300 hectares.</div><div>Another Chinese developer China Fortune Land Development Company Private has also joined hands with Haryana state to develop large format industrial parks in the state. Also, Gezhouba, another prominent Chinese construction company, has in-principle agreed to invest Rs 10,000 crore in irrigation projects in Telangana state.</div><img src="http://static.wixstatic.com/media/577c7f_1d54eec145ee4d17b1f30ee9feda6412~mv2.jpg"/><div> &quot;It will be interesting to see if larger deals are signed in 2016. With China experiencing a slowdown in their own economy, the developers there will get an opportunity to benefit from India's growth story. The Wanda investment will be one of its biggest, so far. It is also bigger than most deals that other Chinese companies investing abroad carried out in 2015,&quot; said Anuj Puri, chairman and Country head, JLL India.</div><div>Even for the Indian real estate industry, it will be among the biggest investments in the residential and retail asset classes by a foreign developer. According to JLL, increased participation by foreign players is expected to help in the development of quality projects, which will benefit end-users and simultaneously create opportunities for Indian investors too.</div><div>&quot;It will be interesting to observe the implications of Wanda's strategy and the innovations such foreign players bring to India as they compete with local players to capitalise on the opportunities that India gives them now. Foreign developers are also going to look at partnering with their Indian counterparts. Interestingly, large residential projects are of particular interest to other Chinese developers. It remains to be seen if commercial asset class also gets on their radar in the near future, &quot; Puri added.</div><div>Apart from Chinese developers, Japanese and Chinese private equity investors are also looking at entering India's real estate sector. Japanese developers are keen to explore strategic partnerships and enter into joint ventures with Indian builders, and are particularly interested in industrial projects. There is likely to be an inflow of at least $ 2 billion investments from Japan into the Indian real estate market over the next three years.</div><div>Other foreign players like Philippe Starck and Trump Real Estate has already entered in Indian real estate market by launching luxury residential projects. </div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Real Estate Bill is an act now, may protect home buyers</title><description><![CDATA[NEW DELHI: The Real Estate (Regulation and Development) Bill, 2016, became an act on May 1, kick-starting the process of making rules as well as putting in place institutional infrastructure to protect the interests of home buyers in India. While acknowledging that the act is a positive development, property experts said the new rules should address problems faced by builders in getting sanctions and approvals in a timely manner. "Government authorities should also be made accounta .. Read more]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/05/25/Real-Estate-Bill-is-an-act-now-may-protect-home-buyers</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/05/25/Real-Estate-Bill-is-an-act-now-may-protect-home-buyers</guid><pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 06:29:14 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>NEW DELHI: The Real Estate (Regulation and Development) Bill, 2016, became an act on May 1, kick-starting the process of making rules as well as putting in place institutional infrastructure to protect the interests of home buyers in India.  While acknowledging that the act is a positive development, property experts said the new rules should address problems faced by builders in getting sanctions and approvals in a timely manner. &quot;Government authorities should also be made accounta .. </div><div>Read more at: http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/articleshow/52069308.cms?utm_source=contentofinterest&amp;utm_medium=text&amp;utm_campaign=cppst</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Real Estate Regulator Bill: 10 things you should know about it</title><description><![CDATA[NEW DELHI: The Rajya Sabha passed the Real Estate Regulator Bill, which will help regulate the sector and bring in clarity for both buyers and developers. Here are 10 things you should know about this bill, touted as a key reform measure in the vast real estate sector. 1) It establishes the State Real Estate Regulatory Authority for that particular state as the government body to be approached for redressal of grievances against any builder. This will happen once every state ratifies this Act]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/05/25/Real-Estate-Regulator-Bill-10-things-you-should-know-about-it-1</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/05/25/Real-Estate-Regulator-Bill-10-things-you-should-know-about-it-1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 06:20:24 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>NEW DELHI: The Rajya Sabha passed the Real Estate Regulator Bill, which will help regulate the sector and bring in clarity for both buyers and developers. Here are 10 things you should know about this bill, touted as a key reform measure in the vast real estate sector.  1) It establishes the State Real Estate Regulatory Authority for that particular state as the government body to be approached for redressal of grievances against any builder. This will happen once every state ratifies this Act and establishes a state authority on the lines set up in the law.</div><div>Read more at: http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/articleshow/51344872.cms?utm_source=contentofinterest&amp;utm_medium=text&amp;utm_campaign=cppst</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>REITs will assist in streamlining the real estate sector</title><description><![CDATA[Real Estate Investment Trusts (REITs) are pooled investment trusts that predominantly invest in completed, revenue-generating real estate properties, manage such properties and distribute a major portion of the earnings to their investors.The concept of REIT was first introduced in 1960s in the United States. Realising the benefits that a REIT provides, other countries (such as Australia, the UK, Germany, Singapore, etc) introduced REIT legislations subsequently. Globally, REITs have]]></description><dc:creator>Abhishek Goenka, Partner- Direct Tax, PwC India (Real Estate expert) | Pallavi Garg, Manager-Tax</dc:creator><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/05/18/REITs-will-assist-in-streamlining-the-real-estate-sector</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/05/18/REITs-will-assist-in-streamlining-the-real-estate-sector</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2016 14:10:24 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>Real Estate Investment Trusts (REITs) are pooled investment trusts that predominantly invest in completed, revenue-generating real estate properties, manage such properties and distribute a major portion of the earnings to their investors.</div><div>The concept of REIT was first introduced in 1960s in the United States. Realising the benefits that a REIT provides, other countries (such as Australia, the UK, Germany, Singapore, etc) introduced REIT legislations subsequently. Globally, REITs have demonstrated the ability to attract and effectively manage investments in the real estate sector. Besides other advantages, REITs bring increased transparency in the sector by adopting better corporate governance.</div><div>In India, the real estate sector contributes significantly to its GDP, however, it continues to be largely unorganised. Despite being a natural hedge against inflation, real estate assets are kept out of the financial market and the common investor is denied the opportunity to share in the returns from this asset class.</div><div>The REIT framework was introduced by the Securities &amp; Exchange Board of India (sebi) in 2014. These regulations are substantially in line with global regulations. A special tax regime for REITs was also introduced by the government of India in 2014 to allow for the tax incidence to be the same as a direct investment in real estate. There are still some niggles, but the recent proposal in Budget 2016 that exempts the distributions made by SPVs (owned by REIT) from the dividend distribution tax of approximately 20 percent has created a tax framework that is actually attractive. The proposed amendment has brought the Indian REIT regime and the related tax framework in line with the global framework.</div><div>In addition to becoming an attractive investment option for non-residents – the government had late last year eased the foreign investment norms to enable this. REITs in India are also expected to provide the common man an opportunity to invest in fixed income securities which also provide long-term capital appreciation. Due to limited investment opportunities, savings made by such investors are usually channelised into gold and housing which are unproductive assets. REITs as an investment class are expected to convert such capital into a productive asset class. It also opens to small investors an arena (i.e. rent generating real estate assets) which was hitherto the monopoly of large investors.</div><div>The real estate sector in India faces severe constraints in terms of adequate and structured finance options. Bank funding to the real estate sector has been sporadic. Although there are recent signs of turnaround in the nature of capital coming into the sector, there is severe shortage of risk capital in the real estate sector and bulk of such capital is in the nature of mezzanine finance.</div><div>REITs, being pure equity capital, will help developers in improving their debt-equity balance and assist in the growth of a more stable and mature market. They would also provide developers with institutional capital to sell their assets and utilise funds for further development or for paring of bank debt. With access to public markets for IPOs not being a short to medium term option for developers in India, this option is all the more attractive.</div><div>It is also expected that the banks in India can be a major contributor of assets in REITs. These banks own vast</div><div>commercial real estate for their offices and branches. These assets can be revalued and swapped into a REIT and the asset can be leased to the banks. This would enable the money raised to flow back to the bank for shoring up their balance sheets, and at the same time be a very stable asset for the investors.</div><div>The global capital allocation towards REITs is also increasing exponentially. With the introduction of REITs in India, allocated global capital for dedicated REITs can be channelised into the country, and with the tax framework being loaded in favour of non-residents, this is a very likely outcome.</div><div>REITs will assist in streamlining the real estate sector by creating a clear mechanism for raising finance in the real estate market. Since REITs operate in a regulated environment, it will bring upon transparency in transactions, thereby instilling confidence in the minds of individual and foreign investors.</div><div>The real estate industry’s need for additional source of funding and global success of REITs is compelling enough to encourage the implementation of REITs in India. The enabling framework and tax regime shows the intent of the government to make REITs a reality. However, one needs to be careful of the quality of assets being launched in the first few REITs, and it is critical that only mature assets with strong leasing and high quality asset management are put out to REITs. This, coupled with the softening in interest rates expected soon (considering the across the board reduction in rates on bank deposits and other avenues such as the PPF), will mean that the returns on REITs could actually start looking attractive.</div><div>All the blocks are in place now for the launch of REITs in India –whether it is the regulations, the tax regime or the overall macro factors and I expect that by early 2017 we should see the first of the offerings.</div><div>Read more: http://forbesindia.com/blog/economy-policy/reits-will-assist-in-streamlining-the-real-estate-sector/#ixzz4915LfyOb</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Home Sales in Canada Reach Record High in April</title><description><![CDATA[FEATURED VIDEOSales of existing homes in Canada reached a record high in April and increased by 3.1% (seasonally adjusted) compared to March. On a non-adjusted basis, actual home sales surged by 10.3% in April.Home sales in April were driven by real estate demand in Ottawa and Edmonton and offset the weakness in the Vancouver real estate market, according to the Canadian Real Estate Association (CREA). The association reported that more than 70% of the region witnessed a gain in activity. CREA]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/05/18/Home-Sales-in-Canada-Reach-Record-High-in-April</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/05/18/Home-Sales-in-Canada-Reach-Record-High-in-April</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2016 14:06:58 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>FEATURED VIDEO</div><div>Sales of existing homes in Canada reached a record high in April and increased by 3.1% (seasonally adjusted) compared to March. On a non-adjusted basis, actual home sales surged by 10.3% in April.</div><div>Home sales in April were driven by real estate demand in Ottawa and Edmonton and offset the weakness in the Vancouver real estate market, according to the Canadian Real Estate Association (CREA). The association reported that more than 70% of the region witnessed a gain in activity. CREA President Cliff Iverson said, “National home sales set new monthly records over the past two months, even as activity in Greater Vancouver and the GTA (Greater Toronto Area) appears to have topped out.” </div><div>Read more: Home Sales in Canada Reach Record High in April | Investopedia http://www.investopedia.com/articles/markets/051716/home-sales-canada-reach-record-high-april.asp#ixzz4914XZhmV </div></div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>What gives you up to 20% rental income in UAE…</title><description><![CDATA[Residential rental yields in Dubai are among the world’s highest, but a new investment category can fetch investors up to 20 per cent. The new asset class, according to Cluttons, a property consultancy, is worker accommodation. “The variety of investment options available in Dubai range from low-end, high-yielding residential units in peripheral schemes such as International City and Discovery Gardens, to more sophisticated investment options in the office market, where yields can range from 6.5]]></description><link>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/05/16/What-gives-you-up-to-20-rental-income-in-UAE%E2%80%A6</link><guid>https://www.realexapp.com/single-post/2016/05/16/What-gives-you-up-to-20-rental-income-in-UAE%E2%80%A6</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 14:07:00 +0000</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><div>Residential rental yields in Dubai are among the world’s highest, but a new investment category can fetch investors up to 20 per cent.</div><div>The new asset class, according to Cluttons, a property consultancy, is worker accommodation.</div><div>“The variety of investment options available in Dubai range from low-end, high-yielding residential units in peripheral schemes such as International City and Discovery Gardens, to more sophisticated investment options in the office market, where yields can range from 6.5 per cent to 9 per cent. We are also witnessing the emergence of worker accommodation as an increasingly popular asset class, which can offer yields of between 10 per cent and 20 per cent,” said Faisal Durrani, Head of Research, Cluttons.</div><div>The Global Property Guide, a website that compiles and analyses property price performance of the world's big economies, has said Dubai offers rental income on average of 7.1 per cent, which is one of the highest in the world. In comparison, gross rental yields in Hong Kong are 2.82 per cent, India 2.22 per cent and Singapore 2.83 per cent, London between 2.72 per cent and 3.20 per cent.</div><div>A number of developers have been projecting rental yields of between 6 per cent and 10 per cent to attract investors/buyers.</div><div>The high rental yield and capital appreciation are among the factors attracting global High Net Worth Individuals to the UAE, with the consultancy’s “2016 Middle East Private Capital Survey Part 2” showing Dubai, Abu Dhabi and Sharjah to have emerged as the most popular investment destinations for the regional wealthy.</div><div>The survey has found 63 per cent of GCC HNWIs planning to invest in real estate during 2016. Of those surveyed, 27 per cent named Dubai as their top three destinations within the GCC, while 21 per cent chose Abu Dhabi and 8 per cent Sharjah.</div><div>In April 2016, a new report by Standard and Poor’s Ratings Services said that lifting of sanctions on Russia and Iran, oil price recovery and a weakened US dollar will strongly benefit the recovery of the property market.</div><div>“We still believe that the lifting of geopolitical restrictions, such the sanctions on Russia and Iran, could strongly benefit the recovery of the UAE property market. This would open new investment flows into the regions' real estate markets and partly compensate for the softening demand from other countries,” the ratings agency said.</div><div>“A rebound in oil prices as well as weakening US dollar would also likely reverse the negative trend,” it added, quoting industry experts that real estate prices have declined by 10 to 13 per cent on average in 2015.</div><div>“The strong US dollar has made UAE real estate more expensive for international investors holding non-US-dollar liquidities, and weaker tourist sentiment has affected retailers and their landlords,” S&amp;P said.</div></div>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>